Guide to the Sally Tatnall papers RL.11335
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Sally Tatnall papers
1953-2016 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Tatnall, Sally
RL.11335
13.5 Linear Feet
Sally Tatnall is a self-described radical feminist and community and political activist from Cleveland Heights, Ohio. Her work centers on lesbian rights, feminism, women's spirituality, reproductive health, anti-racism, and back-to-the-land projects. The collection includes personal materials such as journals, correspondence and photographs, as well as documentation of Tatnall's activism, and printed materials including 1970s sex education pamphlets.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Sally Tatnall papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2016.
Biographical / Historical
Sally Tatnall (b. 1937) of Cleveland, Ohio is a feminist, community, and political activist. Tatnall was the founding Executive Director of Neighborhood Family Practice, a community health center on Cleveland's West Side. She has served on the board of the Women's Community Foundation, worked with a women's Land Project, produced the Radical Thought for Women Conference (1987), and organized the Stop Oppression and Racism group. She is currently active in Old Lesbians Organizing for Change.
Content Description
The collection consists of journals, correspondence, meeting minutes, clippings, workshop materials, conference materials, research, and printed materials. Materials document lesbian feminist activism in Cleveland, Ohio, including marches, demonstrations, a feminist Land Project, Restore Cleveland Hope, an art project based on Judy Chicago's The Dinner Party, and the Radical Thought Conference. Printed materials include What She Wants: Cleveland's Monthly Feminist and Lesbian newspaper, 1970s sex education pamphlets, and a group of zines made by high school students in response to Tatnall's work.
Feminists -- Ohio; Lesbian community -- United States; Lesbians -- Political activity -- United States; Women's health services -- United States; Cleveland (Ohio) -- Social life and customs; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture; Old Lesbians Organizing for Change
- Personal Materials, 1953-2001 and undated
  Scope and Contents
  Primarily consists of journals, correspondence, and photographs.
  - Journals, 1973-1999 and undated
    Contains personal journals, notebooks, and a scrapbook dating from 1973-1999.
    - Personal Journals, 1973-1995 and undated (Box 1)
    - Personal Journal, 1994 and undated (Box 2)
    - Personal Notebook, 1980-1999 (Box 2)
    - Journal, 1975 (Box 5)
    - Agenda, 1975 (Box 5)
    - Journal, 1977 (Box 5)
    - Journal, 1978; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Journal, 1979-1980 (Box 5)
    - Journal, 1980 (Box 5)
    - Journal, 1981 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence and Visual Materials, 1953-2001 and undated
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 1)
    - Cards and Letters, 1984-1987 (Box 1)
    - 60th Birthday, 1997 (Box 1)
    - High School Yearbooks, 1953-1954 (Box 2)
    - Photo Albums (Box 2)
    - Photographs, 1930s-1950s (Box 2)
    - Photographs, 1980s-1990s (Box 2)
    - Letters from Phyllis, 1984-1994 and undated (Box 2)
    - Letters to Sally, 1950s-1990s (Box 2)
    - Letters from Sally to Others, 1975-1986 and undated (Box 2)
    - Notes, 1970s-2001 and undated (Box 2)
    - Financial Correspondence, 1979-1982 and undated (Box 3)
    - Scrapbook, 1982-1985 and undated (Box 9)
- Activism, 1969-2014 and undated
  - Cleveland Feminism, 1973-2014
    - Feminism in Cleveland Skit, 1973-1984 (Box 4)
    - Cleveland Women's Handbook, 1980 (Box 3)
    - Women's Building Fund, 1982-1985 and undated (Box 3)
    - Women's Programs, 1980-1984 and undated (Box 3)
    - Restore Cleveland Hope Strategic and Business Plans, 1970s-2012 (Box 3)
    - Gold Flower Defense, 1970s and undated (Box 3)
    - Protests Correspondence, 1984-2014 and undated (Box 3)
    - Oven Productions Programs, 1970s-1980 and undated (Box 4)
    - Kelly's Island Event, 1988 (Box 4)
    - Wages for Housework Campaign, 1987-2014 and undated (Box 4)
    - A Place for Us Development Inc., 2007-2011 and undated (Box 4)
    - Old Lesbians Organizing for Change (OLOC), 2009-2010 and undated (Box 4)
    - Restore Cleveland Hope (RCH), Strategic Planning Committee, 2000s and undated (Box 3)
  - Land Collective, 1976-2004 and undated
    - The Collective, 1994-2004 and undated (Box 3)
    - Meetings for Collective, 1978-1984 (Box 3)
    - The Collective/Collective Retreat, 1986-1995 and undated (Box 3)
    - Land Collective Maps and Landfest at Egg Moon Farm, 1995-2004 (Box 3)
    - Land Collective Legal Correspondence, 1996-2006 (Box 3)
    - Land Project Correspondence, 1976 (Box 5)
    - Land Collective Meetings, 1995-2005 (Box 3)
    - Land Collective Duplicates (Box 3)
    - Feminist Spirituality Land Project Workshop, 1984-1985 and undated (Box 4)
  - Woofer Tweeter Tapes Essay, 1988 and undated
    - The Woofer Tweeter Theory of Sexual-Stimulus Response, 1988 and undated (Box 4)
    - Woofer Tweeter Tape Drafts 1-10 (Box 3)
    - Woofer Tweeter Drafts Ch. 1-11 (Box 3)
    - Woofer Tweeter Tapes 10-19 Duplicates (Box 3)
    - Writings: Woofer Tweeter Theory of Sexual Stimulus-Response, 1988 and undated (Box 3)
    - Woofer Tweeter Tapes 10-19 Drafts (Box 3)
  - Judy Chicago's The Dinner Party, 1979-1992 and undated
    - Judy Chicago The Dinner Party Slides, 1979 (Box 6)
    - The Dinner Party Negatives (Box 6)
    - Ohio Chicago Art Project, Inc. Judy Chicago's The Dinner Party, 1979-1982 (Box 4)
    - Ohio Chicago Art Project, Inc. Women's Foundation, 1982 and undated (Box 4)
    - The Dinner Party in Magazines, 1980-1992 (Box 6)
    - The Dinner Party Photographs, 1981 (Box 6)
    - The Dinner Party Buttons, 1979-1980 (Box 6)
  - Conferences/Workshops, 1977-2010 and undated
    - Feminist Spirituality Workshop and Medicine Wheel, 1985-1992 and undated (Box 3)
    - Medicine Wheel and Spirituality Workshops (Box 4)
    - Feminist Forum Meetings, 1977 (Box 4)
    - Radical Thought Conference, 1987; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Post-Radical Thought Conference Correspondence, 1987 (Box 3)
    - The National Lesbian Conference, 1991 (Box 4)
    - Retreats and Workshops, 1986-2003 and undated (Box 4)
    - Workshops and Conferences on Aging, 2009-2010 and undated (Box 4)
    - Listing of Women's Events, 1974-1987 and undated (Box 4)
    - Women's Workshops and Events – Materials, 1979-1991 and undated (Box 4)
  - Research, 1969-2008 and undated
    - Sonia Johnson's Book and The Ship that Sailed into the Living Room, 1987-1991 and undated (Box 3)
    - Arousal Myths (Box 3)
    - National Black Justice Coalition, 2008 (Box 3)
    - Daily Devotionals, 1987 and undated (Box 3)
    - LGBT Elderly Issues/Resources, 2004-2008 and undated (Box 3)
    - Feminism, FBI & Judicial Process (Box 3)
    - The Fourth World Manifesto (Box 4)
    - Hymns and Songs (Box 4)
    - Research files, 1976-1979, and undated (Box 4)
    - Feminism and Radical Feminism, 1969 -1975 and undated (Box 4)
    - Resources on Behavior Change, 1974-1988 and undated (Box 4)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1979-1993 and undated (Box 4)
- Printed Materials, 1970-2016 and undated
  - What She Wants: Cleveland's Monthly Feminist and Lesbian Newspaper, 1973-1993 and undated
    - What She Wants Photos (Box 7)
    - Vol 1, No. 1; Vol. 1, No. 3, 1973 (Box 7)
    - Vol. 2, no. 11; Vol. 3, nos. 5-6, 1975 (Box 7)
    - Information and Monthlies, 1981-1993 (Box 7)
    - What She Wants Cartoons, 1990 (Box 7)
    - What She Wants Monthly, January 1988-June 1992 (Box 7)
    - Monthly Newspapers, July 1992-November 1993 (Box 8)
    - What She Wants Resources, 1992 and undated (Box 8)
  - Pamphlets and Zines, 1970-2016 and undated
    - Zines created in response to Sally Tatnall's work, 2016 (Box 8)
    - Copies of The Monthly Extract: An Irregular Periodical, 1976-1978 (Box 2)
    - Notes from the Second Year, Women's Liberation, 1970 (Box 8)
    - Notes from the Third Year, Women's Liberation, 1971 (Box 8)
    - The Gynecological Checkup, undated (Box 8)
    - Plain Talk About Venereal Disease, 1970 (Box 8)
    - Questions Teens Ask About Sex, 1973 (Box 8)
    - You've Changed the Combination, 1973 (Box 8)
    - The Perils of Puberty, 1974 (Box 8)
    - The Inside Story, 1974 (Box 8)
    - Decisions About Sex, 1975 (Box 8)
    - Infections of the Vagina, 1976 (Box 8)
    - High School Women's Liberation, 1976 (Box 8)
    - The Problem With Puberty, 1976 (Box 8)
    - Little Red Book for Citizens over 60, 1977 (Box 8)
    - Teenager's Survival Guide, 1977 (Box 8)
    - So You Don't Want to be a Sex Object, 1978 (Box 8)
    - This Is You, 1979 (Box 8)